<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Death in Videogames</title><link>https://www.deathinvideogames.com/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Death in Videogames</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 22:22:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.deathinvideogames.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Spiritfarer</title><link>https://www.deathinvideogames.com/posts/01-spiritfarer/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 22:22:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.deathinvideogames.com/posts/01-spiritfarer/</guid><description>Game setup In Spiritfarer, the player takes on the role of Stella, who guides souls to the afterlife upon a boat in a fantastical sea. The gameplay is management based, focusing on gathering resources, platforming, and navigating a ship. The goal is to make these souls happy and cared for, so that they can peacefully transition to the afterlife.
How death is represented Narrative: NPCs die and then pass to the afterlife Narrative: Player character dies and passes to the afterlife Thematic: Strong overtones of palliative care Tone Explorative Peaceful Contemplative, reflective Emotional Analysis The role of a psychopomp in videogames tends to be relegated to an NPC perspective in videogames, so it is an unusual approach to have the player assume that role.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/01-spiritfarer.jpg" alt="Spiritfarer"></p>
<h2 id="game-setup">Game setup</h2>
<p>In Spiritfarer, the player takes on the role of Stella, who guides souls to the afterlife upon a boat in a fantastical sea. The gameplay is management based, focusing on gathering resources, platforming, and navigating a ship. The goal is to make these souls happy and cared for, so that they can peacefully transition to the afterlife.</p>
<h2 id="how-death-is-represented">How death is represented</h2>
<ul>
<li>Narrative: NPCs die and then pass to the afterlife</li>
<li>Narrative: Player character dies and passes to the afterlife</li>
<li>Thematic: Strong overtones of palliative care</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tone">Tone</h2>
<ul>
<li>Explorative</li>
<li>Peaceful</li>
<li>Contemplative, reflective</li>
<li>Emotional</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="analysis">Analysis</h2>
<p>The role of a psychopomp in videogames tends to be relegated to an NPC perspective in videogames, so it is an unusual approach to have the player assume that role. Players may be familiar with Charon from Greek mythology, or Anubis from Egyptian mythology. Psychopomps do not judge souls, they merely guide them - and that&rsquo;s the role you play here.</p>
<p>(N.B. confusingly, Anubis in different periods in Egyptian mythology has  taken on the role of both a psychopomp and also of the god of the underworld, where he would weigh your soul against the weight of a feather)</p>
<p>The characters that join your boat crew have presumably already died, and the methods of their deaths are left vague or unanswered. In this spirit realm they take on an animal persona, such as a snake, deer, or frog. As the player cares for each character by completing various tasks, you learn more about them, as they come to terms with how they lived their lives.</p>
<p>The most emotional parts of the game come upon the final journey to the &ldquo;everdoor&rdquo;, the door to the afterlife. Characters only request to be taken to the everdoor once they are ready, and on this final journey they open up, reflecting upon their lives. The player at some points also converses with Hades. It is ambiguous in this context whether Hades the lord of the afterlife, like his namesake in Greek mythology, or a personification like the Grim Reaper.</p>
<p>There is no form of systematic death in Spiritfarer, or even a failure state. There are platforming elements, but the player will always land in the sea, from which they can recover easily. If the player neglects to feed or care for the residents, then they will go hungry and stop providing bonuses to the ship - but they will never die. With no hard failure states, nor a deadline, this gives the game a relaxed tone, as there is no pressure or skill barrier which will prevent the player from achieving their goal.</p>
<p>Although the strict narrative element has you taking on the guise of a ferryman to the afterlife, there are strong thematic overtones of palliative care throughout the entire game. Stella, the player, cares for characters in their last moments, and helps make them comfortable before they leave. It is implied in certain game sequences that Stella was a palliative care nurse in real life, showing her at the bedside of various human characters. My interpretation is that the game serves not as Stella caring for others, but that she has died herself, and this game&rsquo;s story represents her coming to terms with the achievements and events of her own life. The game ends with Stella traveling through the everdoor, marking her own death.</p>
<p><em>Spiritfarer is available on the following platforms:</em></p>
<ul>
<li>Windows</li>
<li>macOS</li>
<li>Linux</li>
<li>PlayStation 4</li>
<li>Nintendo Switch</li>
<li>Xbox One</li>
<li>Stadia</li>
</ul>
]]></content></item></channel></rss>